OLALLA DÍAZ-YÁÑEZ

University of Eastern Finland P.O. 111. School of Forest Sciences 80101 Joensuu, Finland. +358 40 8269912

olalla.diaz@uef.fi / olalla.diaz@gmail.com www.olalladiaz.net

Researcher, teacher and project manager with research experience in forest stand dynamics, forest ecology, forest management, planning and natural disturbances. Creative, problem solver, team-oriented with good communication skills, results-driven with talents in science communication, planning and organisation. Extensive international experience having worked in organisations such as IUFRO HQ, US Forest Service, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, University of Eastern Finland and Polytechnic University of Madrid. Qualifications include:

- Scientific programming and simulation with R
- Data management and visualisation
- Personal organisation
- Time management

- Communication
- Flexibility
- Leadership
- Pedagogical competence

Language

English (full professional proficiency). Spanish (native). French, Swedish & Finnish (basic).

Education

PhD, 2018 — University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu, Finland

MSc Forest Management, 2013 — Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Umeå, Sweden

MSc European Forestry, 2013 — University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu, Finland B.E. Forest Engineering, 2011 — Technical University of Madrid, Madrid, Spain

International

Visiting researcher, University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences (BOKU) Vienna, Austria 2018

visits

Visiting researcher, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station April-August, 2017

Visiting teacher, University of Vigo, Pontevedra, Spain 2016

Visiting researcher, CTFC, Solsona, Spain 2016 Visiting researcher, NIBIO, Ås, Norway 2015 Visiting researcher, CTFC, Solsona, Spain 2014

Experience

Postdoc Researcher, University of Eastern Finland; Joensuu, Finland — 2018-now
I am currently working on evaluating direct and value based trade-offs for ecosystem goods and services in multi-objective management of boreal forest under changing climatic change (Academy of Finland research project OPTIMAM). My work include simulation and optimisation of management alternatives and trade-off analysis of the ecosystem services they provide.

Early Stage Researcher, University of Eastern Finland; Joensuu, Finland — 2014-2018 My PhD research relates forest risk from natural disturbances with stand dynamics and forest management. I have modelled natural disturbances in Norway based on 20 years National Forest Inventory data (about 80.000 observations). I have also developed a stand dynamic simulator and an optimisation algorithm to find forest management recommendations that consider snow and wind damages, evaluate biodiversity, carbon capture and forest development.

Researcher, US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station April-August 2017

During my visit I collaborated with the Resource Monitoring and Assessment team. I used the Forest Inventory data on the west cost of the US to predict the snag standing survival after a fire damage on natural reserves. The main objective was to find out the real value of the snags as habitat and carbon storage.

Project Assistant, IUFRO; Vienna, Austria — (short term) 2012

Assist in the development of the project EcoAdapt and its founding program FORNESSA. Participate in the selection process of founded applicants and write a scientific report.

Research Assistant, University of Eastern Finland; Joensuu, Finland — 2011-2012 Project related to bioenergy, plantations and governance.

Teacher, FESSA (Social Studies Foundation in the Agricultural and Food Sector); Madrid, Spain — 2011

Teacher, course coordinator on forestry oriented courses for forestry professionals.

Researcher, METLA (Finnish Forest Research Institute); Joensuu, Finland — 2009-2010 Investigate constraints for wood procurement in selected EU countries.

Teaching

Over 3 years as a teaching assistant and leader, with experience designing curriculum, developing new teaching tools, grading, overseeing labs and guest lecturing. Courses and seminars include: data science with R, statistical research methods, academic skills, biomass for energy, forest management and planning.

Appointments Editorial board of Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research (2018)

for scientific journals

Reviewer in Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research

Awards / Recognition

Recognition of high quality review in Forestry: An international Journal of Forest Research (2018)

Supervision Co-supervision of two MSc thesis

Service / Leadership

Vice-member in the School of Forest Sciences (UEF) steering committee 2018-Vice-chair of the University of Eastern Finland Doctoral Student Association 2016-17

Board member of the University of Eastern Finland Doctoral Student Association 2014-17

Board representative in the FORES Doctoral school program 2016-

Board representative in the NOVA network (Nordic Forestry, Veterinary and Agricultural

University Network: Denmark, Norway, Finland & Sweden) 2017

Secretary non-profit organisation Edusilva 2015-16

Outreach

PhD mentoring program University of Eastern Finland 2016-17 Coding in school-Teaching code to 4th grade school students

Cultural volunteering - Immigration inclusion, developing leisure programs for children 2015-17

References

Prof. Timo Pukkala

Faculty of Natural Sciences and Forestry. University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu campus PL 111 (Yliopistokatu 7), 80101 Joensuu p. 050 4423 372, email: timo.pukkala@uef.fi

Senior Researcher Vicente Monleon

USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station. Resource Monitoring and Assessment. 3200 SW Jefferson Way, Corvallis, Oregon, United States. p. 97331-8550, email: vjmonleon@fs.fed.us

University Researcher Blas Mola-Yudego

Faculty of Natural Sciences and Forestry. University of Eastern Finland, Joensuu campus PL 111 (Yliopistokatu 7), 80101 Joensuu p. 050 4422974, email: blas.mola@uef.fi